<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide>
<title>Beacon User Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="n9986.mali@gmail.com">

Nandeep Mali

</mail>
</author>


<abstract>
This guide shows you how to set up and use Beacon, a GuideXML Editor. GuideXML is a syntax which is used as official format for Gentoo documentation. This document itself was created using Beacon.
</abstract>

<date>2008-07-07</date>



<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Beacon Design Goals</title>
<body> 

<p>Beacon is a web based WYSIWYG editor for authoring GuideXML 
documents. It allows you to rapidly create or edit documents without knowing the GuideXML syntax by providing a Rich Text Editor Environment. It also allows the user to directly edit the underlying XML for custom changes.</p>



</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Further Resources</title>
<body>

<p>The following links should tell you more about the Gentoo Documentation and GuideXML syntax:
</p>


<ul>
<li>
<uri link="http://gdp.gentoo.org">Gentoo Documentation Project</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">GuideXML Guide</uri>
</li>
</ul>


<p>You can play around with the source code of this document that can be found in the editor's folder.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Getting Started</title>
<section>
<title>Installation</title>
<body>

<p>Beacon needs a PHP enabled web server and a JavaScript enabled browser. Currently supported browsers are:</p>


<ul>
<li>Firefox 2/3</li>
<li>Safari 3 </li>
</ul>


<p>Start off with fetching a copy of Beacon directly from the webserver using GIT.
</p>



<pre caption="Fetching a copy of git"># <i>git clone git://git.tuxfamily.org/gitroot/beacon/trunk.git
</i>
</pre>


<p>Navigate to the <path>trunk/editor/</path> directory. This is the folder that you have to move to your Webserver's httpdocs and you are done!</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Running Beacon</title>
<body>

<p>Point your browser to the folder you have put Beacon in with the correct address. For example if you have put it in <path>httpdocs/beacon/ </path>you would access it by typing <path>http://www.localhost.com/beacon</path>.</p>


<p>You will be presented with the the landing page of Beacon. Here you can choose to create a new document or edit an existing document.</p>


<p> On clicking New you will be presented with a form with the following fields:
</p>


<ol>
<li>
<b>Title of the Document</b>: This is what your document will be called. Try to keep it short and sweet. Can be changed later.</li>
<li>
<b>Author of the Document</b>: Add your name here. Additional authors and email information later.</li>
<li>
<b>Abstract</b>: A summary of the document. Readers should be able to tell with one look what your document is all about.</li>
<li>
<b>Date</b>: Use the standard YYYY-MM-DD format! If you didn't you can change it later.</li>
</ol>


<p>Click Go! to proceed to the editor screen.</p>


<p>On clicking Edit you will be presented with a file upload form. Choose a valid GuideXML file. Click upload and you will be presented with a preview of the document. Click on Go! to proceed to the Editor.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>


</guide>

