<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article id="example-tutorial">
  <title>Beacon - User Guide</title>
  <section id="sn-small-section">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Beacon is a WYSIWYM based XML editor with an emphasis on
clean and sane output. It uses a 'fill in the blanks' approach to web-
based editing and has a plug-in architecture to allow other documentation
types to be integrated as well.</para>
    <para>Currently Beacon is under development but the source can be
obtained from our GIT repository.</para>
    <screen>git clone git://git.tuxfamily.org/gitroot/beacon/trunk.git</screen>
    <para>We try our best to make sure that the tree does not have broken
code! A beta release is not far though. For a more detailed
installation guide please have a look at https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/DocBook_Editor_Documentation.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="cdsfsdf8241_node_85_newNode">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    <para>Once you are setup and ready to go, point your browser to the
Beacon setup and let it load.</para>
    <note>
      <title>Reduce Loading Times</title>
      <para>You can reduce loading time by loading less number of
plug-ins.</para>
    </note>
    <para>When Beacon loads you can see a basic introduction page with
a sidebar on the right. This will be the usual structure of all
document workspaces that you will create in Beacon.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Structure</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>A Sidebar - Has a lot of tools like trees and insert
options.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Main Content – Shows the document itself and some
options on top along with last saved information. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Beacon has a very simple UI. In the next section we’ll
describe how to edit a document. When you create a new document it
opens in a new tab. You can navigate between different tabs and work
on multiple documents simultaneously.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="cdsfsdf8241_node_180_newNode">
    <title>Editing a Document</title>
    <para>Clicking anywhere on the main document will cause an editor
to open up if the node that you have clicked allows editing. While
editing, click anywhere else on the document except the node you are
editing to close the editor. You can alternatively hit the return key
to close the inline editor.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>The top bar above the main content has:</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>Save Button: Saves the document to the server.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>XML View Button: This removes the design view and shows
the raw XML. This can also be edited and the changes will reflect back
to design view. To get back to the design view hit the XML view button again.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Last saved information: This label shows when the
document was last saved.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The side bar has two blocks in an accordion widget. Clicking
on one collapses the other. The default open view shows a document
tree. The document tree shows all nodes in the document. One can focus
the design view on a particular node by double clicking that node in
the tree.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Right clicking a node brings up a context menu with the
following options:</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add sibling before this node</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add sibling after this node</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Delete this node</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The first and second options are used to create new nodes in
the document. When clicked a tree node will appear with a drop down
select box. This select box will contain the list of node that can be
added here. Choose one and you will see it appear in the design
view.</para>
    <para>Below the Document Tree there is a block called ‘Insert
Inline Child’. This is used to insert inline nodes on selected text in
the document. Select a piece of text when using a rich text editor
(say on a paragraph, usually headings do not allow it) and move to the
select box to choose inline type. Select one and click Insert. This
will cause the highlighted text to be wrapped with that particular
inline type.</para>
	<note>
		<title>Populating Lists</title>
		<para>To maintain the sanity of the document, only those child 
and sibling nodes are shown which are allowed by the DocBook DTD for that node.</para>
	</note>
  </section>
</article>